A Guide to the Records of the Secretary of Technology, 1997-2006 (bulk 2002-2005)
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Records of the Secretary of Technology, 2002-2005
The Library of Virginia
43539
30.30 cubic feet (87 boxes)
Virginia Secretary of Technology
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Various items have been sealed for seventy-five years from the date of the document for privacy and/or security concerns.
Acquisition Information
These materials came in several accessions and were combined into one body of records under Acc. 43539. Included are the following accessions: 41045, 42312, and 42495.
Historical Information
In February 1997, the House of Delegates passed a resolution requesting that "the Governor appoint a Technology and Science Advisor within his Cabinet to advise him with regard to technological and scientific issues in Virginia and assist him and executive branch agencies with the potential reorganization or restructuring of Virginia state government in response thereto." James S. Gilmore III, a Republican candidate for Governor, proposed in an April 23, 1997 speech the creation of a Cabinet-level post for an information technology officer. After his election as Governor in November 1997, Gilmore kept his campaign promise. On May 21, 1998, Gilmore issued Executive Order Number Nine, creating the Office of the Secretary of Technology. The new Secretary's responsibilities included the "coordinated planning and effective development of information technology resources" in Virginia. Gilmore appointed Donald W. Upson, a vice president of Litton/PRC Inc, an information technology company, and a former senior Republican committee staff member in Washington, as the first Secretary of Technology. The Secretary of Technology possessed Cabinet-level status but was not officially made a permanent member of the Governor's cabinet until 1999. The Secretary of Technology is appointed by the governor and subject to confirmation by the General Assembly. The Secretary is responsible to the governor for the Department of Information Technology, Department of Technology Planning, Center for Innovative Technology, and the Virginia Information Providers Network Authority.
Governor Mark R. Warner retained Donald W. Upson, the first Secretary of Technology, in an interim capacity through February 2002. George C. Newstrom, Governor Warner's selection for Secretary of Technology, began work on March 4, 2002. Newstrom previously worked with EDS, a global technology services company. Secretary Newstrom oversaw the Warner Administration's technology reform, including the consolidation of all Information Technology services and IT employees in the Commonwealth into a single agency, the Virginia Information Technologies Agency (VITA). Newstrom also worked to fundamentally change the way Virginia government purchases and manages information technology across the state. Newstrom resigned on October 1, 2004 and was replaced by his deputy, Eugene J. Huang.
Scope and Content
The Secretary of Technology records consist of eighty-seven archival boxes and are divided into ten series. Series have been designated for Appointment Calendars, Cabinet Meeting Records, Correspondence & Supporting Documentation, Commonwealth of Virginia's Innovative Technology Symposium (COVITS), Decision Briefs, Projects & Studies, Public Relations, Strategic Plan for Technology, Virginia Information Technologies Agency (VITA), and Virginia Technology Alliance (VTA). These records document the work of the Secretary of Technology under Governor Mark R Warner. The bulk of the records can be found in the Correspondence and Supporting Documentation series which includes background information on many of the technology issues facing the Warner administration. The Virginia Information Technologies Agency series represents the most significant series since it documents the formation of a new state agency to supply the information technology needs for all state government. The Appointment Calendars series provides an important glimpse into the day-to-day activities of the Secretary of Technology.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I: Appointment Calendars, 2002-2006
Series II: Cabinet Meeting Records, 2002-2004
Series III: Commonwealth of Virginia's Innovative Technology Symposium (COVITS), 2002-2005
Series IV: Correspondence & Supporting Documentation, 1997-2005 (bulk 2002-2005)
Series V: Decision Briefs, 2002-2005
Series VI: Projects and Studies, 2001-2005 (bulk 2002-2003)
Series VII: Public Relations, Activities, and Visits, 2002-2005
Series VIII: Strategic Plan for Technology, 2002-2004
Series IX: Virginia Information Technologies Agency (VITA), 2002-2005
Series X: Virginia Technology Alliance (VTA), 2004-2005
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Separated Material
Oversized material has been separated to Box 87.
Contents List
- Series I: Appointment Calendars, 2002-2006., Extent: 24 boxes. (Box 1-24)
  The Appointment Calendars series is housed in twenty-four archival boxes and is arranged in chronological order by the date of the event. This series consists of appointment calendars belonging to Secretary of Technology, George Newstrom, and his successor Eugene Huang, from February 2002 to January 2006. In addition, there are appointment calendars belonging to Eugene Huang in his role as Deputy Secretary between January 2003 and September 2004. This series contains electronic mail, memorandums, cabinet meeting reports, briefing materials, correspondence, invitations, scheduling recommendation/ request forms, agendas, schedule requests, minutes, appointment calendars, speeches, talking points, publications, and other sundry materials.
  This series documents events attended by the Secretary of Technology & Deputy Secretary including cabinet meetings, luncheons, dinners, speaking engagements, Virginia Technology Alliance Board meetings, Information Technology Association of America meetings, Identity Theft Task Force meetings, the Virginia Electronic Commerce Technology Center E-Commerce Forum, the Virginia Technology Summit, Information Technology Investment Board meetings, Virginia Workforce Council meetings, Commonwealth of Virginia's Innovative Technology Symposium (COVITS) meetings, and others. Especially noteworthy are the following events: Governor Warner's Trade Mission to China & Hong Kong (2003 Nov. 13-23), National Association of State Chief Information Officers Conference (NASCIO) (2004 Apr. 25-27 & 2005 Oct. 16-19), World Information Technology & Services Alliance (WITSA) in Athens, Greece (2003 May 14-16) & Vietnam (2003 Nov. 26), Joint Hearing of the Select Committee on Cybersecurity, Science, & Research & Development (2004 Apr. 21), Greater Richmond Technology Council Awards Dinner (2004 May 12), Governor Warner's Trade Mission to Beijing, Shanghai, & Nigbo, China (2004 June 4-13), Northern Virginia Technology Trade Mission to Jordan (2004 Apr. 6), Information Technology Investment Board Meeting (2004 July 7), and the Joint Commission on Technology & Science Meeting at Virginia Tech (2004 Aug. 2-3).
  Arranged in chronological order.
  - 2002
    - February (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - March
      - 3-17 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - 18-29 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - April
      - 1-10 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - 11-17 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - 18-28 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - 29-30 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - May
      - 1-9 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - 10-18 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - 19-30 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - June
      - 1-11 (Box 2, 6 6)
      - 12-18 (Box 3, 6 1)
      - 19-30 (Box 3, 6 2)
    - July
      - 1-15 (Box 3, 6 3)
      - 16-23 (Box 3, 6 4)
      - 24-31 (Box 3, 6 5)
    - August
      - 1-20 (Box 3, 6 6)
      - 21-27 (Box 4, 6 1)
      - 28-30 (Box 4, 6 2)
    - September
      - 1-15 (Box 4, 6 3)
      - 16-17 (Box 4, 6 4)
      - 18-21 (Box 4, 6 5)
      - 22-30 (Box 4, 6 6)
    - October
      - 1-14 (Box 5, 6 1)
      - 15-18 (Box 5, 6 2)
      - 19-27 (Box 5, 6 3)
      - 28-31 (Box 5, 6 4)
    - November
      - 1-12 (Box 5, 6 5)
      - 13-21 (Box 5, 6 6)
      - 22-30 (Box 6, 6 1)
    - December
      - 1-11 (Box 6, 6 2)
      - 12-31 (Box 6, 6 3)
  - 2003
    - January
      - 1-15 (Box 6, 6 4)
      - 16-31 (Box 6, 6 5)
    - February
      - 1-18 (Box 6, 6 6)
      - 19-28 (Box 6, 6 7)
    - March
      - 2-13 (Box 7, 6 1)
      - 14-26 (Box 7, 6 2)
      - 27-31 (Box 7, 6 3)
    - April
      - 1-11 (Box 7, 6 4)
      - 12-30 (Box 7, 6 5)
    - May
      - 1-6 (Box 8, 6 1)
      - 7-15 (Box 8, 6 2)
      - 16-27 (Box 8, 6 3)
      - 28-30 (Box 8, 6 4)
    - June
      - 1-10 (Box 8, 6 5)
      - 11-24 (Box 9, 6 1)
      - 25-30 (Box 9, 6 2)
    - July
      - 1-13 (Box 9, 6 3)
      - 14-18 (Box 9, 6 4)
      - 21-31 (Box 9, 6 5)
    - August (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - September
      - 1-6 (Box 10, 6 1)
      - 7-30 (Box 10, 6 2)
    - October
      - 1-15 (Box 10, 6 3)
      - 16-31 (Box 10, 6 4)
    - November (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - December
      - 1-10 (Box 11, 6 1)
      - 11-22 (Box 11, 6 2)
  - 2004
    - January (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - February
      - 2-18 (Box 11, 6 4)
      - 19-27 (Box 11, 6 5)
    - March
      - 1-25 (Box 11, 6 6)
      - 26-31 (Box 11, 6 7)
    - April
      - 1-24 (Box 12, 6 1)
      - 25-29 (Box 12, 6 2)
    - May (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - June (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - July
      - 7 (Box 12, 6 5)
      - 8-28 (Box 12, 6 6)
    - August (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - October
      - 1-11 (Box 13, 6 2)
      - 12-15 (Box 13, 6 3)
      - 16-28 (Box 13, 6 4)
    - November (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - December
      - 1-10 (Box 13, 6 6)
      - 11-31 (Box 14, 6 1)
  - 2005
    - January
      - 1-20 (Box 14, 6 2)
      - 21-31 (Box 14, 6 3)
    - February
      - 1-10 (Box 14, 6 4)
      - 11-28 (Box 14, 6 5)
    - March
      - 1-9 (Box 14, 6 6)
      - 10-20 (Box 15, 6 1)
      - 21-29 (Box 15, 6 2)
      - 30-31 (Box 15, 6 3)
    - April
      - 2-11 (Box 15, 6 4)
      - 12-20 (Box 15, 6 5)
      - 21-29 (Box 16, 6 1)
    - May
      - 2-12 (Box 16, 6 2)
      - 13-26 (Box 16, 6 3)
    - June
      - 1-6 (Box 16, 6 4)
      - 7-15 (Box 16, 6 5)
      - 16-30 (Box 17, 6 1)
    - July
      - 1-12 (Box 17, 6 2)
      - 13-21 (Box 17, 6 3)
      - 22-28 (Box 17, 6 4)
    - August
      - 1-22 (Box 17, 6 5)
      - 23-31 (Box 17, 6 6)
    - September
      - 1-15 (Box 18, 6 1)
      - 16-30 (Box 18, 6 2)
    - October
      - 1-19 (Box 18, 6 3)
      - 20-31 (Box 18, 6 4)
    - November
      - 1-14 (Box 18, 6 5)
      - 15-16 (Box 18, 6 6)
      - 17-30 (Box 18, 6 7)
    - December
      - 1-8 (Box 19, 6 1)
      - 9-21 (Box 19, 6 2)
  - 2006
    - January 3-7 (Box 19, 6 3)
  - Deputy Secretary
    - 2003
      - January (Box 19, Folder 4)
      - March
        - 4-14 (Box 19, Folder 5)
        - 17-31 (Box 19, Folder 6)
      - April (Box 20, Folder 1)
      - May
        - 1-27 (Box 20, Folder 2)
        - 28-31 (Box 20, Folder 3)
      - June
        - 1-10 (Box 20, Folder 4)
        - 11-30 (Box 20, Folder 5)
      - July
        - 1-24 (Box 20, Folder 6)
        - 25-31 (Box 21, Folder 1)
      - August
        - 1-20 (Box 21, Folder 2)
        - 21-29 (Box 21, Folder 3)
      - September (Box 21, Folder 4)
      - October (Box 21, Folder 5)
      - November
        - 3-15 (Box 21, Folder 6)
        - 16-30 (Box 22, Folder 1)
      - December (Box 22, Folder 2)
    - 2004
      - January (Box 22, Folder 3)
      - February (Box 22, Folder 4)
      - March (Box 22, Folder 5)
      - April (Box 22, Folder 6)
      - May (Box 23, Folder 1)
      - June (Box 23, Folder 2)
      - July (Box 23, Folder 3)
      - August
        - 2-11 (Box 23, Folder 4)
        - 12-25 (Box 23, Folder 5)
      - September
        - 1-15 (Box 23, Folder 6)
        - 16-30 (Box 24, Folder 1)
- Series II: Cabinet Meeting Records, 2002-2004., Extent: 2 boxes. (Box 24-25)
  The Cabinet Meeting Records series is housed in two archival boxes and is arranged in chronological order by the date of the meeting. The series consists of cabinet meeting records belonging to Secretary of Technology, George Newstrom, between March 2002 and December 2004. The series contains cabinet meeting agenda, cabinet weekly reports, meeting notes, memorandums, briefings, legislation, presentations, and other sundry items.
  This series documents weekly cabinet meetings held by Governor Mark R. Warner & William H. Leighty, Chief of Staff, attended by Secretary George Newstrom. Especially usefully in this series are cabinet weekly reports. These reports provide information delivered by Secretary Newstrom in the cabinet meetings regarding legislation, governor's initiatives/special projects including Virginia Information Technologies Agency (VITA), Center for Innovative Technology (CIT), Commonwealth of Virginia's Innovative Technology Symposium (COVITS), etc., agency matters/operations, procurements, events/agency visits, audits/investigations/compliance, stakeholder issues, & pending decisions.
  - 2002
    - March-July (Box 24, Folder 2)
    - August-November (Box 24, Folder 3)
    - December (Box 24, Folder 4)
  - 2003
    - January-June (Box 24, Folder 5)
    - July-October (Box 25, Folder 1)
    - November-December (Box 25, Folder 2)
  - 2004
    - January-June (Box 25, Folder 3)
    - July-November (Box 25, Folder 4)
- Series III: Comonwealth of Virginia Innovative Technology Symposium (COVITS), 2002-2005., Extent: 3 boxes. (Box 25-27)
  The Commonwealth of Virginia's Innovative Technology Symposium (COVITS) series is housed in two archival boxes and is arranged in chronological order by the date of the symposium. The series consists of correspondence, briefing books, news clippings, speeches, programs, media plans, DVDs, and other sundry items.
  This series documents the role of the Secretary of Technology in the planning, sponsorship, & implementation of the Commonwealth of Virginia's Innovative Technology Symposiums held in Virginia between 2002 and 2005. The Commonwealth of Virginia's Innovative Technology Symposium is an annual conference of officials from state & local government, business, and academia to discuss Virginia's technology issues. The series includes speeches delivered by Governor Mark Warner & Secretary of Transportation George C. Newstrom. Also useful within this series is program information and press documenting the symposiums.
  Arranged in chronological order, then alphabetical.
  - 2002
    - Conference Program (Box 25, Folder 5)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 25, Folder 6)
    - Videotapes (Box 25, Folder 7)
  - 2003
    - Briefing Book (Box 25, Folder 8)
    - Closing Remarks (Box 25, Folder 9)
    - Event Program & Guide (Box 25, Folder 10)
    - Governor's Technology Awards (Box 25, Folder 11)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - Opening Remarks (Box 26, Folder 2)
    - Presentations (Box 26, Folder 3)
    - Press (Box 26, Folder 4)
    - Press Releases (Box 26, Folder 5)
    - Remarks (Box 26, Folder 6)
    - Speaker Remarks (Box 26, Folder 7)
    - Speech (Box 26, Folder 8)
    - Teleportec, Inc. (Box 26, Folder 9)
  - 2004
    - Advertising (Box 26, Folder 10)
    - Event Program & Guide (Box 26, Folder 11)
    - General (Box 26, Folder 12)
    - Governor's Speech (Box 27, Folder 1)
    - Media Plan (Box 27, Folder 2)
    - Meeting (Box 27, Folder 3)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 27, Folder 4)
    - Press (Box 27, Folder 5)
    - Remarks (Box 27, Folder 6)
  - 2005
    - Event Briefing Book (Box 27, Folder 7)
    - Event Program & Guide (Box 27, Folder 8)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 27, Folder 9)
    - Sponsorship Letters (Box 27, Folder 10)
- Series IV: Correspondence & Supporting Documentation, 2002-2005., Extent: 41 boxes. (Box 28-68)
  The Correspondence & Supporting Documentation series is housed in forty-one archival boxes and is arranged in two subseries. Subseries have been designated for Constituent Correspondence and Secretary's Correspondence. The Constituent Correspondence subseries relates to correspondence originally sent to the Governor's Office and assigned to the Secretary of Technology. The Secretary's Correspondence documents incoming & outgoing correspondence and legislative files of the Secretary of Technology.
  Arranged in alphabetical order.
  - Subseries A: Constituent Correspondence, 2002-2005., 3 boxes (Box 28-30)
    The Constituent Correspondence subseries is housed in three archival boxes and is arranged chronologically. The subseries contains people summary sheets, electronic mail, correspondence, publications, and other sundry documents.
    This subseries documents correspondence sent to Governor Mark Warner and assigned to the Secretary of Technology. The correspondence includes a people summary sheet from the Governor's Office which provides the name & address of the correspondent, the action required, people associated with the correspondence, and completed steps in responding to the correspondence. Oftentimes, the secretary's letter in response is included in the file. The correspondence in this subseries relates to the following topics: technology products & services, internet, spam, legislation, identity theft, telecommuting, budget cuts, Virginia's Center for Innovative Technology, Department of Information Technology, information technology restructuring, Microsoft, VITA, teachers' computer discounts, COVITS, internet pornography, cell phones, and other topics.
    - 2002
      - February (Box 28, Folder 1)
      - March (Box 28, Folder 2)
      - April (Box 28, Folder 3)
      - May (Box 28, Folder 4)
      - June (Box 28, Folder 5)
      - July (Box 28, Folder 6)
      - August (Box 28, Folder 7)
      - September (Box 28, Folder 8)
      - October (Box 28, Folder 9)
      - November (Box 28, Folder 10)
      - December (Box 28, Folder 11)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 28, Folder 12)
    - 2003
      - January (Box 28, Folder 13)
      - February (Box 28, Folder 14)
      - March (Box 28, Folder 15)
      - April (Box 28, Folder 14)
      - May (Box 28, Folder 15)
      - June (Box 29, Folder 1)
      - July (Box 29, Folder 2)
      - August (Box 29, Folder 3)
      - September (Box 29, Folder 4)
      - October (Box 29, Folder 5)
      - November (Box 29, Folder 6)
      - December (Box 29, Folder 7)
    - 2004
      - January (Box 29, Folder 8)
      - February (Box 29, Folder 9)
      - March (Box 29, Folder 10)
      - April (Box 29, Folder 11)
      - May (Box 29, Folder 12)
      - June (Box 29, Folder 13)
      - July (Box 29, Folder 14)
      - August (Box 29, Folder 15)
      - September (Box 29, Folder 16)
      - October (Box 29, Folder 17)
      - November (Box 29, Folder 18)
      - December (Box 29, Folder 19)
    - 2005
      - January (Box 30, Folder 1)
      - February-March (Box 30, Folder 2)
      - April (Box 30, Folder 3)
      - May-July (Box 30, Folder 4)
  - Subseries B: Secretary's Correspondence, 2002-2005., 39 boxes (Box 30-68)
    The Secretary's Correspondence subseries is housed in thirty-eight archival boxes and is arranged in three sub-subseries. Sub-subseries have been designated for Chronological Files, General Assembly Information, and Legislative Files & Information. The subseries contains correspondence and supporting documentation received by the Secretary of Technology between 2002 and 2005. The Chronological Files sub-subseries is the largest and most useful of the three sub-subseries. It contains incoming & outgoing correspondence of the Secretary of Technology along with supporting files documenting various technology issues. The General Assembly Information sub-subseries provides documentation on technology-related legislation. Lastly, the Legislative Files & Information sub-subseries provides further background information regarding significant technology-related legislation.
    - Sub-Subseries 1: Chronological Files, 1997-2005., 30 boxes (Box 30-59)
      The Chronological Files sub-subseries is housed in twenty-eight archival boxes and is arranged in chronological order, then alphabetical. This sub-subseries contains incoming & outgoing correspondence, publications, reports, legislation, legislative study tracking reports, memorandums, legislative action summaries, news releases, presentations, agency hiring requests, and other sundry items. Correspondence represents the most significant The incoming correspondence includes correspondence sent to Secretary Donald W. Upson, Secretary George C. Newstrom, and Deputy Secretary Eugene Huang, other secretariats, U.S. Senators & House of Representatives, state senators & delegates, state officials, & constituents. This correspondence relates to the following subjects: congratulatory letters, budget, technology products & services, appearances, conferences, meeting, thank-you letters, and legislation. In most cases, the incoming correspondence can be found with the Secretary's outgoing response. This correspondence relates to the following subjects: speaking engagements, legislation, budget, recommendations, COVITS, thank-you letters, conferences, workshops, invitations, technology products & services, technology procurement approvals, WITSA, awards, contracts, Governor's trade mission to Asia, congratulatory letters for appointments to boards & commissions, Virginia's Center for Technology Innovation, employment, and agency hiring requests.
      - 1997
        - Report of the Southern Technology Council (Box 30, Folder 5)
      - 1999
        - Report of the Southern Technology Council (Box 30, Folder 6)
      - 2001
        - Jefferson Lab (Box 30, Folder 7)
        - Report on the Future of the South (Box 30, Folder 8)
        - Report on the Southern Technology Council (Box 30, Folder 9)
        - Report on the Southern Technology Council (Box 30, Folder 10)
        - Technology Forecast: 2001-2003 (Box 30, Folder 11)
        - Virginia Biotechnology/Biomedical Directory (Box 30, Folder 12)
      - 2002
        - Access Solutions Guide (Box 31, Folder 1)
        - Briefing (folder 1) (Box 31, Folder 2)
        - Briefing (folder 2) (Box 31, Folder 3)
        - British Embassy Visit to Richmond (Box 31, Folder 4)
        - Budget Amendments (Box 31, Folder 5)
        - Budget Amendments (Box 31, Folder 6)
        - Cavalier Telephone (Box 31, Folder 7)
        - Center for Innovative Technology (Box 31, Folder 8)
        - Chief Information Officer Advisory Board (Box 31, Folder 9)
        - ComCare Alliance Briefing (Box 32, Folder 1)
        - Commonwealth Major IT Project Status Report Dashboard (Box 32, Folder 2)
        - Commonwealth Technology Fund (Box 32, Folder 3)
        - Congressional Briefing (Box 32, Folder 4)
        - Correspondence - Incoming
          - January (Box 32, Folder 5)
          - February (Box 32, Folder 6)
          - March (Box 32, Folder 7)
          - April (Box 32, Folder 8)
          - May 1-15 (Box 33, Folder 1)
          - May 16-23 (Box 33, Folder 2)
          - May 24-31 (Box 33, Folder 3)
          - June 4-20 (Box 33, Folder 4)
          - June 21-30 (Box 33, Folder 5)
          - July 1-20 (Box 34, Folder 1)
          - July 24-31 (Box 34, Folder 2)
          - August 1-15 (Box 34, Folder 3)
          - August 16-30 (Box 34, Folder 4)
          - August [Undated] (Box 34, Folder 5)
          - September 5-25 (Box 34, Folder 6)
          - September 27-30 (Box 35, Folder 1)
          - October (Box 35, Folder 2)
          - November 4-15 (Box 35, Folder 3)
          - November 18-30 (Box 35, Folder 4)
          - November [Undated] (Box 35, Folder 5)
          - December 2-24 (Box 35, Folder 6)
          - December [Undated] (Box 36, Folder 1)
        - Correspondence - Outgoing
          - January (Box 36, Folder 2)
          - February (Box 36, Folder 3)
          - March (Box 36, Folder 4)
          - April (Box 36, Folder 5)
          - May (Box 36, Folder 6)
          - June (Box 36, Folder 7)